Superior to the mind — buddhi, intelligence,
Превыше ума — буддхи, разум,
the discriminating factor.
различающий фактор.
'cause the mind...
Потому что ум...
We're told accepting and rejecting...
Нам говорят, принимает и отвергает...
... it's doing this indiscriminantly
он делает это безразлично
so the intelligence is there to say
Поэтому есть разум, чтобы сказать:
"Humm, maybe this isn't good for you"
"Хмм, возможно, это не хорошо для тебя"
Or: "yes, this is something you should definitely pursue"
Или: "Да, это то, к чему тебе явно нужно стремиться"
but is that dharma-buddhi?
но дхарма-буддхи ли это?
you know, intelligence under the influence of
Знаете, разум под влиянием
or is that something else?
или это что-то другое?
someone can be extremely intelligent and not be Krishna-conscious
Кто-то может быть крайне разумным, но не сознавать Кришну
it's in the fifth canto of Shrimad Bhagavatam
это в пятой песне Шримад Бхагаватам
saying that someone may appear to be enriched with so many good qualities
кто-то может выглядеть обогащённым столь многими хорошими качествами
but if they're not connected to reality
но если он не соединён с реальностью
by implication that reality means Krishna Krishna-conception
подразумевая, что реальность — это Кришна, Кришна-концепция
then
тогда
there's nothing substantial there, it says
здесь нет ничего существенного, здесь говорится
this is just floating on the chariot of the mind
это просто плавание на колеснице ума
that's another upanishadic example we see
Это ещё один упанишадный пример
we're told that the atma is like the charioteer
Нам сказано, что атма — как возничий
and the senses are like five horses
а чувства — как пять лошадей
and the mind and intelligence 're supposed to be the reigns to guide the senses
и ум и разум должны быть поводьями, чтобы направлять ими чувства
but without the infusion of dharma-buddhi from
Но без инфузии дхарма-буддхи от
what sort of direction would there be?
какое тут будет направление?